Guide to the Samuel Langhorne Clemens Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Samuel Langhorne Clemens Collection
1860-1980
YCAL MSS 852
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.59
(29 boxes) + 3 art, 2 broadside
Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired primarily through gift from Walter Francis Frear and Emma Dillingham Frear, 1942. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Opalotype portraits in box 34: Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
Samuel Langhorne Clemens (1835-1910)
Samuel Langhorne Clemens, who wrote under the pseudonym Mark Twain, was an author and lecturer.
Willard S. Morse (1856-1935)
Willard Samuel Morse, metallurgist and collector.
Walter Francis Frear (1863-1948)
Walter Francis Frear (Yale University, 1885, and Yale Law School, 1890), lawyer, judge, Governor of Hawaii (1907-1913), and collector.
Associated Materials
Associated Material: [Portraits of Mark Twain (Samuel L. Clemens), chiefly original photographs and prints, including busts and statuary, caricatures, family, and residences (Za C591 +G1); [Portraits of Mark Twain (Samuel L. Clemens), chiefly original photographs and prints, including busts and statuary, caricatures, family and residences]: [reproductions, reprints, and clippings] (Za C591 +G2); [Illustrations accompanying articles by or about Mark Twain in various periodicals] (Za C591 +G3) ‡a Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1860-1980. II. Writings, 1870-1968. III. Other Papers, 1872-1960. IV. Artwork and Objects, 1877-1912.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Langhorne Clemens Collection provides insight into the life and career of Clemens, American author and lecturer best known by his pseudonym Mark Twain. The collection is comprised of correspondence, writings, contracts, scrapbooks, clippings, and printed material.
The collection contains drafts, research notes, printed versions, and contracts, which document Clemens' creative process and writing career. Autograph manuscripts can be found in the collection for The Gilded Age, My Debut as a Literary Person, Clemens' translation of Der Struwwelpeter into English, and A Tramp Abroad. Very few of Clemens' autograph manuscripts represent the entirety of a work; due to his popularity among collectors many of his manuscripts were divided and gifted or sold separately. As the collection illustrates, Clemens was deeply concerned with his intellectual property rights, as can be seen in his contracts with publishers and efforts to obtain passage of an international copyright law. Original illustrations for Puddn'head Wilson and A Tramp Abroad can also be found in the collection.
Correspondence with various authors and publishers, including the American Publishing Company, Elisha Bliss, Richard Watson Gilder, Annie Trumbull Slosson, and Joseph Hopkins Twichell, also shed light into Clemens' professional life. Much of the correspondence was removed from printed material. The collection also contains correspondence of collectors Willard Samuel Morse and Walter Francis Frear.
Clemens' celebrity status is evident in a number of items in the collection, such as autographs, a collection of "Some Finger Prints of Mark Twain, Frederic Remington, Joseph Jefferson, and Others," souvenir menus for dinners held in his honor, a bas relief of Clemens and George Cable, and blueprints for a plaque placed on the home where Clemens lived while residing in London, England.
Custodial History
The Frears's collection is largely comprised of Willard Samuel Morse's Collection of Mark Twain.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors and publishers -- United States; Novelists, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Diaries -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Bliss, Elisha, 1822-1880; Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910; Frear, Walter Francis, 1863-1948; Gilder, Richard Watson, 1844-1909; Morse, Willard S. (Willard Samuel), 1856-1935; Slosson, Annie Trumbull, 1838-1926; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, 1838-1918; American Publishing Company (Hartford, Conn.)
- Correspondence, 1860-1962; Series I; 2.3; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Mark Twain Correspondence, Third Party Correspondence, Willard Samuel Morse Correspondence, and Walter Francis Frear Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents Clemens' professional life and personal relationships. The majority of correspondence is comprised of outgoing letters, many removed from printed material in the Beinecke Library's collection, although the series does include some incoming correspondence.
  Correspondents include authors and publishers, such as the American Publishing Company, Elisha Bliss, Richard Watson Gilder, Annie Trumbull Slosson, and Joseph Hopkins Twichell, which combined, offer insight into Clemens' literary circle.
  The collection also contains third party correspondence and correspondence of collectors Willard S. Morse and Walter Francis Frear.
  - Samuel Langhorne Clemens Correspondence
    - Alden, Henry Mills, autograph letter signed, Hotel Krantz, Vienna, 2 pages, 1898 November 2 (Box 1)
      Removed from Morse copy of his Mysterious Stranger (New York, 1922).
      General
      Former call number: 46
    - American Publishing Company, 3 autograph notes signed with initials, and written on postal-cards, Hartford: London and New York City, 1897 March 24; 1903 April 28; 1903 May 11, 1867-1903
      Includes copy of letter from American Publishing Company to Clemens dated November 21, 1867.
      Former call numbers: 42, 175
    - Barnes, Henry B., 3 autograph notes signed, Hartford, 1880 December 6; 1885 January 25; 1886 November 20, 1880-1886
      Former call number: 29
    - Bishop, [William Henry?], autograph letter signed, Redding, Connecticut, 4 pages, 1909 October 11
      Former call number: 87
    - Blackmer, Mrs. Helen Kerr, 4 autograph notes signed, with envelopes, Redding, Connecticut, 1909 March 3-October 30
      Former call number: 72
    - Blackmer, Margaret [Mrs. Erle O. Kistler], 16 autograph letters signed, Bermuda, New York City, and Redding, Connecticut, 4 undated autograph letters signed to Margaret Blackmer, New York City and Redding, Connecticut, undated, 1908 - 1910
      Former call numbers: 73, 74
    - Bliss, Elisha, Jr.
      - 6 autograph letters signed, Elmira, N.Y., Saybrook, Hartford, Connecticut, 1869-1876
        Removed from Morse copies of several of his books.
        Former call numbers: 61-65
      - autograph letter signed, Elmira, N.Y., 4 pages, 1869 July 22
        From the estate of Miriam F. Witherspoon, Worcester, MA (at suggestion of Jacob Blanck and Edward Lazare, 1950 October).
        Former call number: 175.1
      - autograph letter signed with his name "per O[livia]. L[angdon].," Buffalo, N.Y., 2 pages, in the hand of Olivia Langdon Clemens, with manuscript corrections by the author, 1870 May 30
        Hand identified as OLC's by Mr. Skenazy (...) and manuscript recat. 1975 October.
        Former call number: 66
      - autograph note signed, Buffalo, N.Y., 1 page, [1870] November 22
        Removed from a book in the Morse collection.
        Former call number: 69
      - 2 typed letters (carbons), Buffalo and Ampersand, N.Y., 6 pages, typed copies, 1871-1901
        Former call number: 175.2
      - 3 autograph letters signed, Buffalo, Elmira, New York; Hartford, Connecticut, 1870-1880
        Former call number: 67
      - autograph letter in the hand of his secretary, S. C. Thompson, signed by Clemens, London, England, 2 leaves, [1873] July 16
        Pencil note on manuscript identifies hand as that of C. W. Stoddard. Removed from Morse copy of his Gilded Age (Hartford, 1873).
        Former call number: 68
      - autograph letter signed, Edinburgh, Scotland, 1 page, [1873] July 27
        Former call number: 109
        Removed from Aldis copy of his The Gilded Age (London).
    - Bliss, Frank E.
      - 1 autograph note signed, Chicago, 1 page, three photostatic copies laid in; 1 autograph note, signed, written on margins of an advertisement, Paris, 1869, 1894
        Removed from Morse copy of his Innocents Abroad (Hartford, 1869).
        Former call number: 36
      - 1 autograph note signed, Florence, Italy, 1892 October 31; 1 autograph letter signed, London, 1900 February 22, 1892, 1900
        Removed from Morse copy of his Adventures of Tom Sawyer (New York, 1910) and Mark Twain's Library of Humor (New York, 1888).
        Former call numbers: 38-39
      - 7 autograph letters signed, various places, [1872]-1902
        Former call number: 37
      - autograph letter signed, Vienna, Austria, 1 page, final page only, containing P. S. signed with initials, [1897? November 4?]
        Former call number: 80
      - autograph letter signed, London, 1900 April 25, 2 pages, 1 leaf
        Former call number: 23
    - Braithwaite, Robert, autograph letter signed to S. L. Clemens, Dover, England, 4 pages, in appreciation of his work, 1897 September 6
      Former call number: 161
    - Brown, John, autograph letter signed, Hartford, Connecticut, 9 pages, [1874] February 28
      Removed from Morse copy of his Gilded Age (Hartford, 1873).
      Former call number: 31
    - Brown & Gross, Books & Stationery, autograph note, signed, asking for a copy of Memoir of Ralph Waldo Emerson by James Elliot Cabot (Boston: Houghton, Mifflin and Company, 1887)
    - General Bryce, autograph letter signed, Rouen, 2 pages, 1894 October 13
      Removed from Morse copy of his Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc (New York, 1896).
      Former call number: 88
    - Chatto, Andrew, typewritten copy of letter, Hartford, Connecticut, 1882 March 30
      Removed from Morse copy of his Prince and the Pauper, London, 1881.
      Former call number: 45
    - Chatto & Windus, autograph letter signed, La Bourboule-les-Bains, France, 2 pages, 1894 July 2
      Former call number: 194
    - Christ, Reverend Frederick V., typewritten letter signed, Redding, Connecticut, 2 pages, 1908 August 28
      Former call number: 30
    - Cist, Lewis Jacob, autograph note signed, 1 page, 1876 August 1
      Removed from Morse copy of his Roughing It (Hartford, 1872).
      Former call number: 89
    - Clagett, William H., Carson City, typed copy (carbon), 1862 February 28
    - Clark, Charles Hopkins, "Charley," autograph note signed, New York City, 1884 November 23
      Removed from Morse copy of his Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (New York, 1885).
      Former call number: 90
    - Clemens, Jane ("Jean") Lampton, final page of autograph letter signed to his daughter, signed "W. D. Howels[!]", undated
      S. L. Clemens' complaint of the government written to the "editor of the N.Y. Times." Clemens sent this draft to his daughter, writing in a postscript that the letter is signed W. D. Howells "because it will have more weight." [Removed from Morse copy of W. D. Howells' My Mark Twain (New York, 1910).
      Former call number: 51
    - Clemens, Orion, 2 typed letters (carbons), Buffalo, N.Y., 6 pages, typed copies, no year March 10-11, 13
      Former call number: 175.3
    - "Dear Colonel," autograph letter, Riverdale, N.Y., 1 page, in the hand of and signed by, an amanuensis, 1903 January 12
      Former call number: 167
    - Drake, J. R., autograph letter signed, Buffalo, N.Y., 1 page, [1870?] December 26
      Removed from Aldis copy of his Adventures of Tom Sawyer (San Francisco, 1876).
      Former call number: 110
    - Fischer, Mr., autograph note signed, Riverdale-on-Hudson, N.Y., 1 page, 1902 January 3
      Removed from his Person Sitting in Darkness (1901).
      Former call number: 91
    - Foote, Mrs., 2 photostatic copies of an autograph letter signed, 3 pages, [18]87 December 2
      Former call number: 57
    - Frisbie, T. S., autograph letter signed (facsimile), Vienna, Austria, 2 pages, 4 copies, with a photographic and a printed reproduction of the photograph to which the letter refers, 1897 October 25
      1 copy, with note by Morse, from Morse collection. 2 copies from estate of Miriam F. Witherspoon. 1 copy (poor condition) gift of A. Rowden King.
      Former call number: 178
    - Fuller, Frank
      - autograph letter, Naples, Italy, 3 pages, 1867 August 7
        Copy in an unidentified hand.
        Former call number: 174
      - 2 autograph letters signed, Washington and New York City, signature on receipted bill made out to Grank Fuller, and dated 1880 March 6. Together with the envelope addressed by Mr. Clemens, [1867] -1894
        Former call number: 35
    - Gerhardt, Karl, 2 autograph letters signed, Elmira, N.Y., pages, 3 pages, respectively, 1 autograph letter signed to Karl and Josephine (McClellan) Gerhardt, Hartford, 8 pages, 1884-1885
      Former call numbers: 59, 77
    - Gilder, Richard Watson
      - autograph letter signed, 2 pages, enclosing "Explanatory [note]" for his play "Meisterschaft" as printed in the Century Magazine, 1888 January, autograph manuscript, 3 pages, 1887 September 28
        Removed from Aldis copy of Century Magazine (January 1888).
        Former call number: 106
      - 2 autograph letters signed, Vienna, 1898 April 2, 1899 February 25
        Removed from Morse copy of his Man That Corrupted Hadleyburg (New York, 1900).
        Former call number: 49
      - autograph letter signed, Hotel Krantz, Vienna, 5 pages, 1898 November 6-13
        Former call number: 50
    - Gillis, James N., 2 autograph letters signed (photostat), Elmira, N.Y., 7 pages, negative and positive photostats, 1870 January 26, no year July 26
      Former call number: 176
    - Goodman, Joseph T., 6 autograph letters signed, Hartford, autograph letter signed to Joseph T. Goodman, Munich, 6 pages, [1879?] January 23, 1889-1890
      Removed from Morse copy of his Tramp Abroad (Hartford, 1880).
      Former call numbers: 32, 33
    - Hall, Mr., autograph note signed, Paris, 1 page, 1894 March 31
      Removed from Morse copy of his Prince and the Pauper (London, 1881).
      Former call number: 86
    - Handy, Mr., autograph letter signed, Hartford, Connecticut, 1 page, 1885 December 29
      Removed from Aldis copy of his Rambling notes of an idle excursion (Toronto, 1878).
      Former call number: 105
    - Hapgood, Norman, autograph note signed to Samuel Langhorne Clemens, New York City, 2 pages, [1903?] February 6
      Former call number: 120
    - "To the Harpers," autograph copy, made by him for Frank E. Bliss, of parts of letter to Harper and Brothers, 3 pages, undated
      Former call number: 40
    - Harte, Bret, autograph note signed, Westminster Hotel, [New York City], 2 pages, 1867 May 1
      Former call number: 71.1
    - Jones, ---, autograph letter, signed, addressed to "My dear Jones," Hartford, 7 pages, 1880 [i.e., 1879] November 7
      Former call number: 76
    - Jones, F. Duncan, typewritten letter signed, Tuxedo Park, N.Y., 1 page, 1907 May 27
      Removed from Morse copy of his Christian Science (N.Y., 1907).
      Former call number: 92
    - Judd, A. Francis, photostat copy of an autograph letter signed, Buffalo, 5 pages and envelope, [1870?] December 20
      Former call number: 28
    - Lewis, Harriet, autograph letter signed, Galesburg, 7 numbered leaves, with a description of the letter: "What I know about Mark Twain," by Harriet Lewis Paff [q.v.], [1868?] January 10
      Former call number: 151
    - Editor of The Literary World, autograph letter signed, unidentified correspondent, 1 page, written in the margins of page 106 leaf extracted from The Literary World, [1873?]
      Removed from Aldis copy of his Innocents Abroad (1869).
      Former call number: 183
    - Lyon, I. V., autograph note signed with initials to his secretary, Miss I. V. Lyon, written on margin of first page of autograph letter signed to him from the Reverend Joseph Hopkins Twichell, 1906 September 14
      Former call number: 34
    - "Dear Madam," autograph letter signed, Elmira, N.Y., 1 page, 1881 September 19
      Removed from Morse copy of his English as She is Taught (London, 1887).
      Former call number: 179
    - "My dear cousins," autograph note signed, Hartford, 1 page, 1889 April 10
      Former call number: 52
    - Monahan, Michael, autograph letter signed (positive photostat), New York, N. Y., 2 pages, with reference to Monahan's article "Saint Mark," printed in his Palms of Papyrus (East Orange, N.J., 1908) p.[47]-53, no year January 28
      Former call number: 188
    - Norris, [Charles G.], autograph letter signed, Innocence at Home, Redding, Connecticut, 3 pages with envelope, positive photostat, 1908 September 19
      Enclosed is typewritten copy of letter with correspondence of Mr. Willard Morse concerning it.
      Former call number: 144
    - Osgood, James Ripley
      - autograph letter signed, 2 pages, [1875] July 20
        Removed from Morse copy of Lotos Leaves, 1875.
        Former call number: 47
      - autograph letter signed, Hartford, Connecticut, 4 leaves, with reference to a footnote eventually printed on page 142 of his The Prince and the Pauper, 1881 October 21
        Removed from Rosenbloom copy of his The Prince and the Pauper (1882).
        Former call number: 208
      - autograph letter signed, 2 pages, 1882 July 19
        Former call number: 164
      - autograph letter signed, 1 page, [1883?] January 15
        Removed from Morse copy of his Suppressed Chapters.
        Former call number: 165
    - Parkhurst, L. E., autograph note signed, [Hartford], [1889] December 20 (Box 2)
      Removed from Morse copy of his Connecticut Yankee, (New York, 1889).
      Former call number: 94
    - Pears, Muriel, 14 autograph letters signed, v.p., with envelopes, 1901 - 1905
      Former call number: 100
    - Perkins, Miss, autograph letter signed, Hartford, 1 page, 1880 April 30
      Former call number: 155
    - Powell, autograph letter signed to Dr. Powell, Tuxedo Park, New York, 2 leaves, from original in possession of W. L. Pforzheimer, 1907 May 27
      Former call number: 143.1
    - Pugh, ---, autograph note signed addressed to "My dear Pugh," Edinburgh, 2 pages, [1873] July 27
      Removed from Morse copy of his Gilded Age (London, 1873).
      Former call number: 27
    - Putnam, George Haven, autograph note signed to Putnam, Hartford, 2 pages, undated
      Removed from Morse copy of his Stolen White Elephant (Boston, 1882).
      Former call number: 56
    - Redpath, James
      - autograph letter signed to Redpath, 2 pages, 1860 May 10
        Removed from copy of his Roughing It (Hartford, 1872).
        Former call number: 70
      - autograph letter signed to Redpath, Hartford, Connecticut, 1 page, [1874] February 13
        Endorsed on verso by Redpath: "Mark Twain, Febr'y 15, 1874." Removed from Aldis copy of his Old Times on the Mississippi (Toronto, 1876).
        Former call number: 111
    - Rideing, William, autograph letter, signed, to Rideing, 1894 February
      Written on "The Players" letterhead and mounted with a portrait drawn by F. Souli Campbell (New York City).
    - Riley. ---, autograph note signed addressed "Dear Riley," Elmira, N.Y., 1 1/4 pages, 1871 March 27
      From Charles S. Boesen's American and English Literature.
      Former call number: 152
    - Riley, James H., autograph letter signed to Clemens, Philadelphia, 2 pages, 1872 May 16
      Former call number: 128
    - Robinson, Henry C., 8 autograph letters signed and 1 autograph postcard signed to Robinson, 1 autograph letter signed to "Mrs. Robinson" (undated), 1 autograph letter signed to Lucius Robinson, London, 2 pages (1 leaf), 1893-1900
      Former call number: 146
    - Schlesinger, Sigmund, 1 autograph letter signed to Schlesinger, with photostat of original addressed envelope, undated
      Former call number: 193
    - Scotland, Riverdale-on-Hudson, autograph note signed, addressed "Dear Scotland", 1902 December 15
      Former call number: 101
    - "Dear Sir," autograph letter signed, (positive photostat), London, England, 1 page, 1899 November 8
      Former call number: 181
    - Skrine, Mr., autograph letter signed, Sanna, Sweden, [1899] September 15
      Former call number: 156
    - Spalding, Mr., Hotel Metropole [Vienna], autograph letter signed, positive and negative photostats laid in, 1897 November 20
      Former call number: 55
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, autograph note signed, Hartford, 1 page, 1889 May 18
      Removed from Morse copy of Lotos Leaves (Boston, 1875).
      Former call number: 95
    - Taylor, Bayard, autograph note signed, Hartford, Wednesday, 2 pages, undated
      Former call number: 54
    - Ticknor, Benjamin H.
      - autograph letter signed, Elmira, N.Y., 1881 September 9
        Removed from Morse copy of his Prince and the Pauper (Boston, 1882).
        Former call number: 48
      - 4 autograph letters signed, Branford, Elmira, and Hartford, 8 pages; 1 autograph note signed to Messrs, James R Osgood and Company: Branford, 1 page, 1881-1885
        Removed from The Prince and the Pauper (Boston, 1882).
        Former call number: 104
    - Trumbull, Annie, 20 autograph letters signed, 1885-1903
      Former call number: 145
    - Twichell, Joseph H., 70 autograph letters signed to Twichell, Elmira, N.Y., Redding, Conn., including a few undated letters and fragments, letters of 1893 November 20 and 1901 April 24 are represented by typed copies only, 1868-1909; 73
      Includes: 1. Autograph letter signed (rough draft) to Baroness Bertha von Suttner [1899] May 7, Vienna, Austria, 1 page, Enclosure to his autograph letter signed to Joseph H. Twichell, [1899 May] which is written at the foot and on the verso of a printed invitation addressed to Clemens by the Baroness von Suttner. 2. The Battle of Ivry Man for His Own Hand Being a Campaign Anthem. Air -- Jerusalem The Golden. Autograph manuscript, 1 leaf, an 8-line poem concerning Hurst [i.e., William Randolph Hearst], enclosure to his autograph letter signed to Joseph H. Twichell, 1907 January 26. 3. Autograph letter (draft) to His Excellency His Italian Majesty's Ambassador, Manchester, Mass. [1903 July 21] Elmira, N.Y. Enclosure to his autograph letter signed to Joseph H. Twichell, 1903 July 21.
      Former call numbers: 128, 149, 159, 162
    - Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, 3 autograph letters signed, Paris, France, Elmira, N.Y., and Rome, Italy, 12 pages, [1879]-1892 (Box 3)
      Former call number: 202
    - Walker, Mr., autograph letter signed, London, England, 2 pages, 1900 September 27
      Removed from Aldis copy of The Man That Corrupted Hadleyburg (1900).
      Former call number: 107
    - Warner, Charles Dudley
      - signature on autograph letter in handwriting of his secretary, Charles Warren Stoddard, London, 3 pages, [1873] July 16
        Former call number: 96
      - autograph letter (fragment), Germany?, 2 pages; pages numbered 9 and 10, concerning Joseph H. Twichell and apparently sent to him, 1878 August
        Former call number: 158
    - Webb, Charles H., autograph letter signed, Darjeeling, 2 pages with envelope, 1896 February 16
      Removed form Morse copy of his Celebrated Jumping Frog (N.Y., 1867).
      Former call number: 97
    - Whitmore, Mrs.
      - autograph letter signed, Elmira, N.Y., 2 pages (1 leaf), with typewritten copy and 2 carbons, 1903 July 18
        Former call number: 147
      - autograph letter signed, New York, N.Y., 2 pages, with a reference to William Lyon Phelps, [1907?] February 7
        Former call number: 71.2
    - Wiggin, Kate Douglas [Mrs. G. C. Riggs], autograph note signed, New York City, 1905 December 6